Mss.497.3.H35o
American Philosophical Society
John Gottlieb Ernestus Heckewelder letters, 1816-1822, to Peter Stephen Du Ponceau
Mss.497.3.H35o
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet Ca. 115 items
Letters relating to American Indian languages, Moravian missionaries, various Heckewelder publications. Some of the replies from Du Ponceau are copied in the letter books of the Historical and Literary Committee.
Ca. 115 items.
Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Peter Stephen Du Ponceau, 1840.
Existence and Location of Copies note
This collection is also available on microfilm (Film 1268).
General note
Printed in part in Transactions of the Historical and Literary Committee of the American Philosophical Society 1 (1819): 351-450.
Biographical/Historical note
John Gottlieb Ernestus Heckewelder (1743-1823) was a missionary of the renewed Unitas Fratrum, or the Moravian Church to the Native American tribes of Ohio. He retired from active missionary service in 1786. In 1792 he was appointed to a U.S. Government commission headed by General Putnam to arrange the Peace Treaty of Vincennes. In 1801 returned to Gnadenhűtten to administer the Indian “estate” on the Muskingum. In 1810, at the request of Caspar Wistar of the American Philosophical Society, Heckewelder recorded his knowledge of Indian life, published as an “Account of the History, Manners, and Customs of the Indian Nations, Who Once Inhabited Pennsylvania and the Neighboring States,” that appeared in Transactions of the Historical & Literary Committee of the American Philosophical Society, vol. 1 (1819).
Heckewelder was the son of a Moravian clergyman and native of Moravia, who served the church of the Unitas Fratrum in England. He was born in Bedford, England, and started his education in Moravian schools there, before moving with his parents to Bethlehem, Pennsylvania in 1754. There he finished the last three years of his education at the Moravian Boys’ School. Afterward, he was sent to assist in the operation of the Economy Farm of the Moravian Brethren at Christian’s Spring near Nazareth. He was indentured to a cedar cooper or barrel maker in Bethlehem, although he expressed a strong interest in evangelism and asked that he be allowed to participate in the work of David Zeisberger and Christian Frederick Post, Moravian missionaries to the Indians on the Muskingum River in the Ohio territory. In 1762 he got his chance, when Post asked him to assist with the transfer of several groups of Christian Delawares from the Susquehanna river area to Ohio. Plans for the migration were temporarily suspended by Pontiac’s War in 1763, and between 1763-1771 Heckewelder was forced to remain a cooper, only occasionally being dispatched as a messenger to the Indian settlement at Wyalusing, Pennsylvania, as well as other Indian towns along the western Susquehanna.
Heckewelder displayed a remarkable understanding of native American customs and languages, spending hours studying their language, traditions, and legendary history. In 1771 he began regular mission duties for a period of fifteen years, during which he was an assistant to David Zeisberger. He lived among the Moravian Christian Indians, guiding Indian groups from the Susquehanna to the Big Beaver River and beyond to Schoenbrunn and Gnadenhütten on the Muskingum river in western Pennsylvania. During those years he was constantly on horseback, leading groups of Indians between Bethlehem and Detroit. He served as their “passport” and guide since the notion of Indians as peaceful and God-fearing people was incongruous to many frontier people. Toward the end of the Revolutionary War in 1781, Heckewelder and all of his companions were taken prisoner by a wandering band of Loyalists and Indians, who held them as American spies in Upper Sandusky, Ohio. He was twice summoned to Detroit by the British authorities and arraigned before the English commandant of the post. During his absence from the Ohio territory in 1782, ninety-six Christian Indians at Gnadenhütten were massacred by white settlers.
In 1780 Heckewelder married Sarah Ohneberg of Nazareth, Pennsylvania. Six years later he retired from active missionary service and moved to Bethlehem, where he continued to be active in church work. However, the new government of the United States soon utilized Heckewelder’s expertise with Indian languages and culture, calling on him as an adviser to the War Department in 1792. Secretary of War Henry Knox asked him to accompany a commission led by General Rufus Putnam to negotiate the Treaty of Vincennes, recognizing American ownership of the Vincennes tract by the Miami Indians. The following year he advised a similar delegation, consisting of General Lincoln, Colonel Pickering and Virginia Governor Beverly Randolph, involved in negotiations with the Iroquois, leading to the Pickering Treaty or the Treaty of Canandaigua. Finally, in 1801 Heckewelder returned to Gnadenhütten, where for nine years he administered the Indian estate on the Muskingum river held in trust for Delaware Indian descendants by the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel. By this time most of these Indians had been transferred to Fairfield, Canada through Heckewelder’s efforts.
In 1810 Heckewelder and his family returned to Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, where new labors awaited him. Caspar Wistar of the American Philosophical Society, solicited his efforts in recording his knowledge of Indian life. The resulting work, an “Account of the History, Manners, and Customs of the Indian Nations, Who Once Inhabited Pennsylvania and the Neighboring States,” appeared in Transactions of the Historical & Literary Committee of the American Philosophical Society, vol. 1 (1819), translated into German and French editions. Heckewelder died in 1823.
Scope and Contents Note
The John Gottlieb Ernestus Heckewelder Letters written to Peter Stephen Du Ponceau, Secretary of the Historical and Literary Committee in 1815 and President of the American Philosophical Society from 1827-1844, represent the Moravian missionary’s responses to the Committee’s inquiries on the languages and cultures of native American peoples. Of the 113 letters, written over a span of seven years (April 3, 1816-May 5, 1822), a selection of thirteen letters from 1816-1818 were published in the Transactions of the Historical and Literary Committee of the American Philosophical Society (Vol. 1,. 1819). In Du Ponceau’s report as Corresponding Secretary, he explains that Heckewelder was a “respectable missionary,” who was identified to the Committee for his “intimate knowledge... of the languages and manners of various Indian nations, among whom he resided for more than forty years.” Not only did Heckewelder author An Account of the History and Manners and Customs, of the Indian Natives, who once inhabited Pennsylvania and the Neighboring States for the first volume of the Committee’s Transactions, he also lent it German manuscript copies of (the late) David Zeisberger’s Grammar of... the Lenni Lenape or Delaware Indians, and his “copious vocabulary of the same language.” Heckewelder’s role as an authoritative resource for information about native American languages and cultures was critical for the linguistic endeavors of Duponceau and the A.P.S. Historical and Literary Committee. Much of the correspondence responds directly to specific questions from the Committee, such as a June 24, 1816 letter titled Answers to Queries on Indian Words. He answers their first query on the Lenni Lenape use of double consonants by explaining these are often necessary for proper pronunciation of a word and in many instances allow the speaker to be “distinctly heard”. Other letters offer more general observations, such as one related in a letter of May 27. 1816. There Heckewelder relates the statement of a certain “French Gentleman,” whom he encountered while living among the Muskingum between 1773-1781. The Frenchman maintained that the Lenape language had such a “wide” range, that he had traveled more than a thousand miles among Indian nations by whom he was well understood. Table of Contents Available
Early American History Note
The John Heckewelder Collection consists of an assortment of documents, almost all of which deal with Native Americans. Heckewelder was a Moravian missionary to Delaware Indians in Pennsylvania who was a prominent figure in nineteenth century intellectual circles. The primary focus of the collection is on his attempt to preserve Native American languages, especially those of the Lenni Lenape (Delaware) in Pennsylvania. His correspondence and one publication also chronicle Native American history, customs, and life. Heckewelder also kept a meteorological journal while on his mission to Gnadenhutten, Pennsylvania from 1802-1814, which is part of the collection. Much of the collection comes from Heckewelder’s correspondence with the APS and its prominent member and linguist Stephen Du Ponceau.
Summary of Collection: There are many content rich sources in the collection. Heckewelder’s “Communications to the Historical and Literary Committee” is a 187-page bound volume of correspondence that includes responses to queries on Indian history, his own observations of Native culture, and records of Native American oral histories as conveyed to Heckewelder ( 970.1 H35c). The record provides insight in Native American history, white understanding of Native cultures, and oral traditions in the early nineteenth century. Among the oral histories Heckewelder records is a contact story, the history of the “emigration” of the Lenni Lenape from the west, and origins stories of other Native groups as related by the Delaware.
The collection also contains his extensive correspondence with Peter Du Ponceau on Indian culture and language (497.3 H35o). The content of these letters add additional details that were not included in his publications or other writings.
Also of significance are his notes on the names that the Lenni Lenape called areas of the Mid-Atlantic that also contain a list of important Indian leaders ( 497.3 H35n). These brief biographical sketches are based on details provided by Indians or Heckewelder’s own interactions with them.
Finally, remaining portions of the Heckewelder Collection contain detailed meteorological data for Gnadenhutten ( 551.5 H352) and other language data.
Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844; Diaries; Indians of North America--Languages; Language and Linguistics; Language Material; Meteorological Data; Native America; Native American Materials; Oral History
- Papers
  - Letter to [Caspar] Wistar, April 3, 1816; 10-1/2x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Scope and Contents note
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p. (see Heckewelder. Letters...; pp.1-2.) Printed: APS Hist.& Lit.Comm. Trans., v.1, p. 363
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, May 27, 1816; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters...; pp.3-6.) Printed: APS Hist.& Lit. Comm. Trans., v.I, pp.366-369.)
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, June 20, 1816; 13x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters..., pp.7-10.) Printed (under totally different arrangement, and not complete): APS Hist. & Lit.Com. Trans., V.I, pp.377-381.)
  - Letter to [Peter S. DuPonceau], June 24, 1816; 7-3/4x6-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    A.L.S. 4p. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.11-14.) Printed: APS Hist.& Lit.comm. Trans., v.I, pp.382-383.)
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, June 29, 1816; 13x7-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.15-18.) Forwards material to the society pertaining to Indians of the U.S.
  - Letter to [Peter S. DuPonceau], July 22, 1816; 7-3/4x6-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L. 14p.and end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.19-34.) Printed (under totally different arrangement, and incomplete): APS Hist. & Lit.comm. Trans., v.I, pp.338-391.)
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, July 31, 1816; 13x7-3/4 and 6-1/2x4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end.and enc.of 4p. ''Pr Favor Dr. Wistar'' (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.35-40.) Concerning Indian linguistics and sends list of Indian words.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Aug. 14, 1816; 13x8 and 7-3/4x6-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Enc.of of 9p. End.as to which letter Heckewelder answered. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.45-60.) Printed: (under totally different arrangement, and incomplete); APS Hist.& Lit.comm. Trans., v.I, pp.410-414.)
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Aug. 23, 1816; 8x6-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.61-64.) Will answer his letters as soon as he can.
  - Letter to [Peter S. DuPonceau], Sept. 20, 1816; 8x6-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    A.L.S. 4p. End.: "Answer to Letter of 3d Augst 1826." (see Heckewelder. Letter; pp.41-44.) Concerning Indian linguistics.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Sept. 27, 1816; 13-1/4x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.65-66.) Concerning Indian languages.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 5, 1816; 13x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.67-68.) Questions whether the Hist.and Lit. Comm.want his Indian vocabularies. Refers to Caspar Wistar.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Dec. 11, 1816; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.69-72.) Concerning his narrative of the Indians. Refers to Wistar, J. Vaughan, and Vanuxem.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Dec. 23, 1816; 10-3/4x7-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.73-76.) Concerning correspondence between Barton and Zeisberger about the Indians. Refers to Wistar and the Historical committee.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Jan. 4, 1817; 10-3/4x7-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.and end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.77-80.) Concerning the publication of his work on the Indians.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, April 13, 1817; 12-1/2x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p. and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.81-86.) Friendly letter. Encloses paper on Indian linguistics taken from a letter by Dencke. Refers to Wistar, Vaughan and Vanuxem.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 23, 1817; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.87-90.) Sympathy for the death of his wife. Is writing on the Indians.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Dec. 2, 1817; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.91-94.) Personal news. Concerning his writing on the Indians. Errors in writings on the Indians by other authors.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Nov.1, 1818; 13x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters...; pp.235-238.) Concerning his publication. Refers to Wistar and Zeisberger. Concerning the Indians' languages.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Jan. 27, 1818; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.95-98.) Death of Wistar.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, March 11, 1818; 9-3/4x7-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add;end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.99-102.) Will send the Committee papers dealing with Indian affairs, in the hands of B. Franklin, Weiser, Parsons, and Horsfield. Concerning an article by Zeisberger.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, March 30, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.103.-106.) Concerning the study of the Indian languages. Will send additional old letters for the committee. Concerning Wistar.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, June 4, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.107-110.) Concerning his work on the Indians. Refers to Zeisberger. Concerning Indian languages. Refers to Correa de Serra.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, June 14, 1818; 10x7-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.111-114.) Will be very happy to have him and Correa de Serra visit. Refers to J.Vaughan.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, June 27, 1818; 9-1/2x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.115-118.) Concerning and anecdote concerning the Indians and a Col. Arent Schyler De Peyster. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, July 3, 1818; 8x6-1/2; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end.and enc.of 5p. (see Heckwelder. Letters; pp.119-126.) Forwards additional notes on the Indians.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, July 8, 1818; 11-1/2x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.127-130.) Corrections for his publication. Concerning the Indians of Pennsylvania. Friendly letter. Refers to the committee
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, July 12, 1818; 10-1/2x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.131-134.) Forwards volumes for the APS by Dencke.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, July 23, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.135-138.) Death of Steinhauer.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, July 29, 1818; 11x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.139-142.) Corrections for his publications. Is forwarding a dictionary, by Zeisberger, of the Indian languages.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, July 30, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add;end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.143-146.) Concerning his publication. Concerning Zeisberger's manuscripts on Indian languages. Refers to Steinhauer and C.W. Peale.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Aug. 6, 1818; 11-1/2x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckwelder. Letters; pp.147-150.) Suppositions on the origin of the Indians. Concerning his publication.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Aug. 12, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 4p. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.151-154.) Concerning the Indians. Concerning Zeisberger. Friendly letter. Printed:Ethnohistory,v.6,no.1,1959, 70-78. Article by E.Wheeler-Voegelin.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Aug. 18, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.155-158.) Corrections and additions for his publication. Concerning Indian languages.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Aug. 22, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.159-162.) Concerning the Indians and their languages.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Sept. 3, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.163-166.) Concerning the Indians. Refers to Correa and Gambold. Concerning Indian languages.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Sept. 5, 1818; 13x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.167-170.) Meaning of friendship to the Indians. Anecdotes defining friendship with them. Refers to Zeisberger.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Sept. 13, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.171-174.) Friendly letter. Concerning Indian names.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Sept. 20, 1818; 10x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.175-178.) Corrections for his publication. Concerning Indian languages. Refers to the Committee and Wistar.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Sept. 21, 1818; 13x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.179-182.) Concerning Indian languages. Corrections in his publication.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Sept. 27, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.183-186.) Concerning his Publication. Refers to Wistar. Concerning Indian languages.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 1, 1818; 13x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    [received] A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.187-190.) Forwards errata for his publication. Refers to Wistar and the Historical committee.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 1, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.191-194.) Concerning his publication.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 3, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckwelder. Letters; pp.195-198.) Concerning his publication. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 7, 1818; 10x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.199-202.) Concerning his publication on the Indians. Concerning Indian languages.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 10, 1818; 13x7-3/4; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters; pp.203-206.) Concerning his publication. Refers to Wistar.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 13, 1818; 13x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters...; pp.207-210.) Corrections for his publications. Concerning Indian linguistics. Refers to Wistar.
  - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Philadelphia, Oct. 14, 1818; 13x8; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Heckewelder. Letters...; pp.211-214.) Copies letter from Dencke concerning Indian linguistics.